You run a swarm to do code review, file a bunch of bugs.
whatever.
You're generating work by spending tokens.
And then you've got a bunch of work, and then you just swarm it to fix it,
and then you swarm it to review it, and then you start over it again.
Right.
And so the factory is pushing the work through.
So when you start talking about software factories, it's the moment
that you start thinking about work as a first class entity,
Oh, no. Oh!
and I'll just
introduce our guest speakers today.
So we're going to have a chat.
And we've got through some amazing speakers with us today.
First group Dru Knox who is the head of product at AI at Tessl.
So he's a former Chrome and web platform PM.
He's worked deep in the web standards, and he's a former research scientist
at Grammarly.
He started his own startup as well and that was very exciting.
And he is an incredible product team.
And if you have if you want to find anyone
that can come up with insane ideas and also execute them using them
and see, I don't think he needs to much of an introduction,
but if you want a small city of the things that he's
he spent over 40 years in the engineering and industry.
He's worked in some incredible companies like Amazon,
Google and most recently at Sourcegraph.
He is a famous essays.
I'm sure some of you have come across some of the work that he's done.
The author of the original Google Platforms rant,
and many other incredible articles that have come come forward,
and also some amazing and frontier level software
like Gastown and Beats
for your external memory issue for agents. So.
I'm going to let them tell everyone
a little bit about themselves as well, and then we'll kick on with the subject.
Thank you very much.
Thank you Simon.
Again, secondary.
Thank you for subbing in 5 or 10 minutes notice.
So welcome everybody.
Glad to have you all here.
So I'll serve as a little bit of MC conversation
partner though I don't kid myself who everybody's here to to hear from.
So I'll try to leave as much time for Steve as possible to to chat.
We're going to go over a few things today, I think, all largely
around the topic of harness engineering and factory building.
So eagle eyed viewers may have noticed the slides.
The title is changed just ever so slightly,
a sign of how fast our industry moves.
Terms have emerged in the three weeks from when we finalize the title to now.
So we want to talk about a little bit what is harness engineering?
What are software factories? What do they look like?
Give a couple examples.
From what we've seen just in our own building
as well as from customers, and then we'd love to just talk about
what kind of impact it's going to have on software
development, on the role of being a software engineer.
You know, where should we be afraid?
Where should we be happy, all of these things.
And then we'll leave a bunch of time at the end for questions.
So if you have thoughts, things you'd like to ask, please
be thinking of them now.
Nothing is worse than asking for questions and getting silence.
So please, please come up with questions.
Now before we get started though, Steve, is there anything you'd like
to say add to your introduction or anything like that?
Thanks all for coming. Looking forward to this.
Awesome.
So I will kick us off with what is a software factory?
Some of you may or may not have heard the term emerging.
It's kind of becoming the new trend we fun thing to build.
So I thought maybe we could start off with probably one of the more notable
first incarnations of something
that looked factory like, which would be Gastown.
Love to hear. Steve.
Just from your perspective, what, in your words, is a software factory?
What does it look like?
What does it feel like to build one? How?
How AI psychosis inducing is it?
Yeah.
So it's a little a little amorphous, right?
I mean, like we're still defining these words, but
I mean, kind of the way I think about it is you get into factories when you start
getting into trying to be a puppeteer for agents
in any sort of capacity.
So if you're using the agent directly, it's not a factory, it's pair
programing with agents. Right.
And if you're writing code that's making agents do stuff.
Yeah. Then you've entered factory territory.
That's that's what I think.
Yeah. Yeah, I think that aligns
I think that
aligns pretty well with at Tessl we view it similarly.
Like there's no one specific definition of a factory.
Right.
It is largely of are you building a system that gets humans out of the loop.
And I think it tends to emerge most obviously as soon as you really start
kind of cooking with agents, like you're a few parallel sessions,
you're putting up PR's much faster than you have previously.
You sort of find that anywhere a human is in the process,
a bottleneck emerges, and it sort of drives you towards a world
where, how can I get the end to end product delivery to be handled by agents?
Yeah.
It's like it's like the moment that you get AI psychosis,
that's when you start thinking about software and batteries, right?
Because that's like they can do it.
They they can do it, you know like unsupervised.
Right. And then you're like, well, they probably need a little supervision.
And then you're like, well, I can't have another agent look over their shoulder.
And then you got yourself an adversarial pod and it's already in a mini factory.
Right. And, you know, we're fine.
I mean, also, you know, like there's
a whole bunch of different surfaces where factories are showing up.
And we first noticed them when we were doing development.
Right. And that's how Gastown came about. Right?
Which was, well, what if I want to run 20 agents at once, right.
You know, I mean, you're not probably like
interacting with 20 directly, like, and guiding them.
You know, the cognitive overhead gets really hard at like 4 or 5, right?
But you have a lot of tasks that can be paralyzed.
You need to do a refactoring or any sort of a sweep, you know.
And and what I found, like, I don't know, it was it last year.
Yeah.
Gastown was gosh, time is fine.
Gastown was January 1st.
So I spent all last year
trying to get agents to like, you know, like run agents, right.
And what I found was that you just you, you frequently needed basically do
there's a there's a, there's a,
there's a rhythm to it.
Right.
You run a swarm to say generate a bunch of reports, a bunch of issues.
Okay.
You run a swarm to do code review, file a bunch of bugs.
Right.
Run a swarm to do an audit to see how, you know, whatever.
Convert all your to do whatever.
You're generating work by spending tokens.
And then you've got a bunch of work, and then you just swarm it to fix it,
and then you swarm it to review it, and then you start over it again.
Right.
And so the factory is pushing the work through.
So when you start talking about software factories, it's the moment that you start
thinking about work as a first class entity,
as a substance that you're manipulating.
Right?
The work, the tickets, the design documents,
the to dues, whatever they are, however, you're representing your work.
And so I sort of backed into this, stumbled into this when I was trying to.
I was running a bunch of parallel
agents by hand, and they were getting just lost and markdown files.
And that's where Beads came from. Right?
Which was just like, okay, what if we just like,
tracked the work in a graph with git and database access and,
and just had a way to like just, just store it all away and watch it
and go through its life cycle of its to do work.
Now it's in progress work
and now it's finished work, which is like a ledger, right?
Those are three very different like views of the work.
When it's future work, it's usually very public.
Anyone can claim it, you know, anyone can debate it and modify it.
Once somebody claims it, it gets exploded out, like the car goes into the shop
and goes up on the stilts and, you know, it's all over the place.
There's lots of maybe little intermediate tickets you're working on.
You usually don't want to see people to see you working in that.
We'll come back to that.
And then and then at some point you actually turn it into a nice digest
and you submit it, it gets reviewed, it gets accepted.
And now it's your now it's your finished work which becomes your resume.
I mean, these are like ants rights, which is like your curated view
of what you've accomplished.
I mean, that's the world that we're headed to.
And Beads formalizes this in a way, right?
I mean, it's like a you can use any issue tracker you want,
but I see a lot of people like defaulting to GitHub issues or linear or something.
And those things are those things are designed to be super heavyweight.
But we're doing software factories.
I mean, did did you all read Welcome to Gastown when I wrote that on January 1st?
I mean, like the core idea was that it's shoveling a lot of work through, right?
To so much to where like in a software factory, you can, like,
accidentally do the same work twice.
Yeah, at the same time you get different outcomes and then somebody has to judge
which one to pick, you know, or you can you can just lose work.
You can do a whole bunch of work, spend the tokens and then where to go.
Right. Somebody deleted it, you know, it's gone. Right.
So like work becomes almost like an uncountable.
Right. And so it's I don't know, right.
I mean, like, it's incredibly expensive to work that way.
But Gastown was me kind of trying to figure out how to push forward.
The funny thing is, though, like, you guess town is, like really overkill
if you really want to, like, you really want to run 60 agents, right?
Recently I haven't been using Gastown, but I've still been building my own
software factories.
You just you get into the habit of building them all the time.
They're bespoke.
You don't have, like, one factory fits, all right?
Like, there are some commonalities.
Like, I'm finding that for each project, you need to build a brain.
Right?
Who use obsidian for that?
It's a really good default. Right.
But you can use whatever.
Anything else for a brain.
What do you use?
G brain?
Is that a Google open source thing or.
No, it's a get help.
From Mary Tam that directly gates obsidian brain.
But Gary tend to the thing.
Wow. Okay, I'll check it out.
I was sure it was no shame in that.
All right.
Yeah, the brain and there's some other components that you put together.
But I mean, largely your factory is like you shaping the
how the work's going to go through your agents. Right.
And the one just to finish it, like the one, the one that I'm working on
right now, the one that you should all be working on right now, is okay
for the next six days.
You want to do a bunch of design work
and file implementation work.
That's that's clear enough that Opus can do it right
for who knows how long, right?
You need. Right. So.
So this is a factory shape.
You're producing work to be consumed later.
Right.
So how you choose to set that up like or later on
if you're going to need Fable occasionally and maybe you'll be stuck with API
access only.
So you need to like basically tag your work with intelligence
tiers in a way so you could route it and know what you stable.
Right.
And so that the setup that you have on your local machine or with your team
or in your org for having these agents swapped
in and out for the appropriate work so that you can save tokens.
That's your that's your factory, right?
Whether you've been explicit about it or not, that's that's what you've got.
I think there's a lot of great topics in there.
Maybe I will put the one about building your own factory.
Everything is bespoke to it later.
Something that has great touches on what is the sort of future of software
engineering if we move into a world of factories.
But you also, I think you outlined a few of those,
the commonalities, the things where when you're building a factory,
you're always going to touch on some of the same topics.
And so maybe to make this concrete within Tassell,
we have been embarking on a bit of a I think it felt at first
like an overambitious goal to see what the limit was and has quickly
become the way we're building now of moving towards a factory.
So I'll walk through some of the main components.
How we're building at tehsil.
I will withhold doing too much of a product pitch, though.
I will just say once we've built most of it with tassels.
So if you're interested, take a look.
That'll be it.
So it started with two core goals that we wanted to get done.
The first is no human written code
and the second was no interactive coding agent sessions.
Sort of like just those two goals pretty much forces you to move into
software factory territory.
So the flow that we've settled on,
I think it'll touch on some of the pieces you talked about.
First thing is everything starts as an issue.
And so I think pretty much immediately, if you're thinking about building
a factory, the first question you have to ask is how are you going to track work?
How are you going to define it? How are you going to manage it?
How are you going to sort of sling it around in Gastown parlance?
So for us we use linear within within heavyweight.
You are right.
Sometimes we wonder if it's if we need all of it.
So what we do is we file tickets.
Those tickets, we then have a background orchestrator that is polling linear.
Basically every time I take it as created, it will pick up anything that you
delegate to the dark factory agent,
what we've called it built internally.
And then an agent picks up that work.
It creates a PR all effectively.
We started with some orchestration,
like trying to do automatically put up the PR for the agent.
We found that frequently broke.
So instead we just give the agent GitHub CLI.
It puts up the PR when it's done.
Then we as an engineering team engage at the PR level.
So we review.
So that brings in another one talking about code review both
from humans and from agents.
It's going to be another area that you're quickly going to find is crucial.
You guys do the same.
No human code review either.
Say again no human code review.
That's a long term goal.
Long term goal, but takes a little bit more work than the first two pieces.
We do have a general.
When you review the code before you directly leave comments
and try to correct the agent immediately, you take a step back and you think about,
how could I have fixed the harness, fix the overall system
that the agent is acting in so that it wouldn't have made this mistake?
And so we had one requirement.
We asked of people before you leave any comments on the PR
at least once, you have to rewind and make changes to either
skills in the code base or add some unit tests.
Change the architecture,
do something that you think could have fixed it and try again.
And then if it doesn't one shot
the second time, then you can just leave comments on the PR.
That's I mean, a really interesting observation
is that no matter how you build yourself or factory, it
basically has an ongoing hygiene and maintenance component.
This was a big deal in Gastown.
It's what the dogs wound up being being for.
They were a dedicated role.
But I mean, like, it doesn't matter how you do it, you're
just going to have to spend some tokens on maintaining the factory.
And so if you can I mean, like if you can build it into your your process
so that everybody leaves it a little better than when they found it.
Right?
So like, you know, because every time you use the factory
you're going to notice that it's slightly bit rotted somewhere, right?
It's just like it's just the natural.
The skills evolve, the systems change, and the skills are effectively
to the new documentation.
So they need updates and things like that. Right.
And we'll talk about how Tessl can help there.
Right.
But it's a really interesting sort of like a mindset.
Right. Which is you have to it's like a workshop.
Like a mechanics workshop, right.
Or a craftsman's workshop.
They got to keep it clean, and they got to spend
a certain amount of time on their tools.
And many of these are going to be totally turnkey.
You're going to you're going to want to build
the maintainer roles into your factory, I think is what I'm saying.
Yeah, yeah.
And that's a great point.
So I think getting started
issue tracker that can immediately delegate into an agent.
It puts up a PR you can leave feedback on.
The PR agent will address those and put up changes.
That's kind of like your core unit.
Every factory is going to want something that looks like that.
And it it might sound, I don't know, to to some folks as
an advanced place to start, but I actually find that agents are pretty good now.
So it's not like you're going to be constantly correcting every single
PR that comes up.
The important piece, though, is starting to work in this way.
All of your interactions with the agent become very legible.
So you have the ticket, you have all of your PR
comments, you have the PR like the commits themselves.
As a result, it becomes very easy to
then start building these kinds of maintenance agents or sweeps,
which is kind of like the next thing that usually emerges within a factory is
that no matter how good your code review is, something slips through somewhere.
And this is probably true of humans as well.
And so you want to set up a set of,
let's call them just like outside of a diff.
But just like general scan the code base once a day, once a week,
you had any sort of cadence you one and just look for ways to improve.
So ones that will typically show up that we have
internally at Tessl are an architecture agent.
So one that just looks for areas of code duplication or week.
Seems that might be hard to test something
that looks through your test quality.
So how's your coverage looking?
Maybe does mutation testing or looks to see?
Are there any new areas of the code base that could be tested better?
Documentation?
There's the list can kind of go on and in fact probably will go on.
Like you'll just keep adding things as you find issues.
And then probably the last one that I'll say, and this maybe
we'll complete the intro to software factories we can go into.
Some of the other topics are code review.
In general, you're going to quickly develop a whole slew of solutions there.
You're going to have general code review that just looks for things
you haven't thought to catch.
Claude has a code review tool that can do this.
There's Code Rabbit.
You can build your own Tessl's tools to help you set one up with a skill.
And then you also want to have more targeted code
review to look for the things that basically the philosophy should be.
Anytime you find a mistake with the agent,
you should never have to correct it again.
There should be something that looks for that specifically.
And this actually I'm curious, Steve, if this resonates with you.
This was like a big change for me was how pedantic your linting
can get in a software factory world, because you're asking agents to write.
It doesn't actually matter if it's you're spending, you know,
50 lines of code to write a linting rule that just checks to see.
Did they make sure that this file never imports from that file
because agents frequently invert the architecture?
An example of this on a side project,
I was building my own agent orchestration tool.
Who hasn't at this point,
and I had a client for working with anthropic and a client
for running the agent turn loop, and I said the harness
should call anthropic, and anthropic should not know about the harness,
and instead the harness implemented its own anthropic client.
And then the anthropic client imported that and exported it
to the rest of the code base.
So I just wrote a linting rule that said, like
the anthropic module should never import from the harness module.
It's not really the kind of thing I would have written
as a linting role in the past, but it feels much more natural to do now.
So I'm curious, have you seen anything like that in the past, like in the way
that you verify the code that is created, any changes
from sort of like historical, like what you would have done, hand coding?
Yeah.
I mean,
so like one of the one thing you got to worry about is
if you just put don't do this, don't do that, you know, over and over again,
then you're going to really want to set a evals that like
tell you, do you still need that when the next model drops.
Right. Yeah.
Otherwise you're going to accumulate forever and kind of be useless.
So I think that's just another another example of another sweep.
You're probably going to want to set up regularly to go and basically
reevaluate every single rule that you put in. Yep.
Yeah, yeah. Another kind of core competency.
And maybe this is a good a good segue into how the profession is changing.
Thinking through like as models are released,
do they solve problems that you couldn't solve before?
I think you've heard
you use the term like pocket evals or something of your hard tasks
that the best model can't currently do, but maybe the next one can.
But there's the inverse to there's may be glue work that you've done
to get the current generation of models working that is no longer needed.
How are you going to tell when that happens?
How are you going to strip out the context, the rules,
the hooks that you had added that are no longer needed?
Yeah.
So like that's the new job, right?
I mean, like software factories ultimately are going to install 24 over
seven autonomous agents that are performing all of the business
processes that that the company is performing now.
And we're going to babysit them. Right.
And that kind of maintenance is exactly part of the stuff that we're going to make
sure it gets done.
And as our ambition grows and our factories grow, right,
those those things that we're doing by hand
get skills, get built, they get pushed down into the infrastructure.
We're looking at higher level concerns. Right.
And and the whole thing has to be it has to be growing constantly.
But it also has to be forgetting constantly.
Right.
Like mathematically, it's becoming really clear that
forgetting is an intrinsic part of any functioning memory store.
Otherwise they get dementia and go insane, right?
Or just become wrong.
So. So yeah, you're building almost a living system.
Do you think that as we build factories, they'll ever be a stable point,
like a moment where you're like,
your factory is done and it just produces the work for you? Or.
I mean, I think the
ceiling just keeps going up for what a factory can build for you.
And then above that ceiling
enters engineering and craftsmanship and taste and.
Right.
I mean, until we've built
the actual literal Death Star, there will always be more work to do.
You know, like, I just like, you know, it's funny, the guy that
the guy at anthropic that I saw from talking to you on Monday,
who was saying that internally they feel that they are ambition bound
now, right?
It's just like it's getting incredibly hard to even just think what to do.
Right.
So yeah, I mean, the job is, is is changing super, super fast.
Will it ever get stable at this point?
It wouldn't bank on it.
What do you think?
If you had to sketch out like two years from now,
a day in the life of a software engineer, what do you think they're
what are they doing?
What are the skills they should be building?
Well, hopefully they have very good work
life balance.
And they come in with their coffee in the morning and they look at their team
of 200 agents and go, all right, let's get started.
How did everyone do? Right.
I mean, it's kind of what we do right now and where we sort of their.
So yeah, I mean like look,
roles are collapsing.
Maybe ideal company sizes are shrinking a little bit.
Right.
But I mean like ultimately
everybody's scared that the introduction of these software factories
is going to reduce the workforce because the factories are doing
a bunch of work that we were doing by hand.
But there's really two
kinds of companies in the world, and I think most of them are the
the ambitious kind.
There's the kind that have one thing to do,
and all they care about is making it more efficient.
Right.
And those those companies can probably shrink.
But I think most companies secretly want to do a lot more than they're doing now.
And they're just going to realize that once all these things are deployed
and they've got all that yak
shaving out of the way, that they can finally, like, set their sights high.
Yeah.
And I'm personally feeling this right now just with my own,
my video game that I've been working on for 30 years.
I counted up my bug backlog during Covid and I had 100 years of work.
This is from players and bug reports, feature requests,
and me, my own things that I wanted to do.
And eventually the backlog backed up to 100 years and I gave up.
Right.
And now, you know, I have ambition to spare, right?
So, yeah, I mean, I just never lose sight of that, right?
Because you'll get really depressed if you start thinking about,
oh, God, they're doing all the work now.
What even value do I bring?
Don't think about it that way.
Think Death Star, right.
Or whatever your North Star is.
I heard a couple things in there that definitely resonate,
like collapsing roles.
So probably folks who were more specialist, like,
I just write really good code, or I just know how to talk to users.
Going to be a little bit more general purpose.
You're going to want to be able to self-serve a little bit of design,
a little bit of product, probably a lot of engineering discipline.
Also, you mentioned what sounded like maybe backlogs are kind of gone, right?
So you're pushing a lot more parallel features,
task switching, multitasking.
I'm kind of curious, how do you feel?
I don't know what kind of engineer you were before agents,
but it does feel like the I'm just going to go sit in a cave for a while
and just think really hard about this one problem.
Nobody's going to talk to me for three days, and I'm going to emerge
with this beautiful, pristine piece of scalable architecture.
It feels like some of that's gone away now.
It's a lot more
juggle five features at once, sort of checking in on them as they go.
Do you?
Does that make you happy? Make you sad?
Indifferent?
I mean, it's all about the dopamine, isn't it?
In the end, what are you going to get it from?
Right.
I used to get dopamine hits from implementing Bresenham's algorithm.
I'm not making this up.
All right.
I'd see a line draw a pixel at a time on this ancient CRT.
And, you know, 1991, in University of Washington.
And I'd be like, yeah, I'm a programmer, right?
But I didn't really want to draw a line.
I wanted a video game. Right.
And so graphics programing has changed dramatically.
Right?
And now we do the stuff that we really wanted to do.
So I mean, I see yeah, I wrote a lot of beautiful code in my game.
I wrote a really nice implementation of a star search,
which is a really fantastic search algorithm, especially for games.
And I wrote a really lovely kernel and scheduler and property system.
And, you know, I locked myself up for days at a time and.
Right.
And that's a wonderful kind of aspect of the job that's kind of gone now.
Right?
But I didn't want to write a star search.
I wanted monsters to chase me.
Yeah.
I mean, you got to, like, remember what you're in it for, right?
And you're in it for outcomes.
You're in it for experiences, you know, you're in it for delivery.
And ultimately, that kind of fun that we were having along the way
was, you know, temporary.
I still get some of the buzz from coding just by like
making the making the A's go rewrite it, you know, to be better.
And then I look at the output and I'm like, yeah,
you know, you get them vibes a little bit, right? Yeah.
But you know, it's it's a new it's a new world, right?
I mean, I liken it to a dog sticking their head out the window.
You get the smells way faster. Right.
You know it's nice.
It's also nice to have one smell and, you know, kind of like it, you know.
Right.
But I don't know, it's just we're headed towards a faster a faster world.
Yeah I've definitely noticed to that.
Like dopamine hit a lot of times.
Some I get just from crafting the system.
I'm sure there's lots of folks in here who love the
I've built my beautiful little worlds that this agent talks to that agent,
and then this check runs and all of that is like,
everybody wants to build their own workflow engine.
At least at Tessl we do.
We love workflow engines.
There were 50 of them at Google when I left.
I was keeping an inventory of workflow engines that engineers
had built at RGB for Grube Goldberg machines.
Yeah, yeah.
Yeah yeah.
You also get to spend a lot of time thinking
about architecture, technical design in some sense.
Some of the more I don't know what people might have called,
like the elevated parts of the job, the senior architect,
the visionary aspects kind of everybody gets to work on those now,
like the drudgery of writing code, I call it
call it drudgery to dig up the architecture.
I know some people really enjoy just the actual crafting of good code,
but it allows all of us to move up a level,
probably the things that we aspired to and move it to your point,
keeping a focus on that, on where you had wanted to go in your career,
probably was moving to some of the things that now
we get to work on more with, with the coding agents.
Yeah.
I'm curious though, do you think there are any, any risks,
any things that we should be
particularly vigilant as we move into this world of factory
building and more agent review of code, less human review of code.
Like anything we should hold on to.
Yeah.
I mean, yeah, I mean, I don't know, we,
we got we got to learn the lessons by, by doing it.
Right. So you know, go burn tokens.
The big lesson I think we all learned is from January through April.
You could argue that Gastown kicked it off in a way was token maxing.
Right.
And the industry just went through a love affair with token maxing.
That was a lesson that we had to learn, which is that
first you have to teach people to spend tokens like their token spend
will go through some step functions, but then when they once they actually
know how they become pigs and you have to teach them to not spend tokens, right?
It becomes like the new challenge.
So you know, yeah, if you enable copilot for your whole org,
you run the risk of blowing your AI budget for the year by two months later, right?
Two weeks later.
So so we've noticed, actually, drew and I independently came
to this conclusion is that there's a there's a training problem ahead.
Right.
There's an enablement problem.
Yeah. Like orgs like people.
People don't know how to do a coding let alone build software factories.
Right.
But I would argue that
every knowledge worker in the next 12 months
has to level up to at least the baseline level
of AI literacy, of being able to use an agent to help them with their work.
Right. And that's a huge it's not that bad.
It only takes five hours,
according to Netflix, of good training for the light bulb to go on.
Until then, they're all terrified that AI is going to take their job,
and after that, they're excited to have the conversation about how they can.
They and their agent can help. Right.
So so this this is what we run into is we talk about
software factories to companies who haven't even started using agents yet.
Right.
And and we're talking kind of talk and past them.
So there's a huge I think we would call it a risk.
But the risk is that we don't train people.
And all of a sudden there's a big train wreck, right?
Companies don't operate properly anymore.
Yeah, I think with factories in particular,
to your point, it can often be presented as this frontier,
this thing for the people who are like some greenfield startup that's just
getting started working 996 totally AGI pilled.
But really, at the end of the day, it's
just a matter of finding repeated workflows and automating them.
Like it can be a very just, piece by piece task.
It doesn't have to be scary.
It doesn't have to require a lot of advanced capabilities as you go.
It's just a dedication to working in a particular way,
taking a step back and automating things.
And I think that's a lot of the training you want to do, right?
You want to show people how to view the problems that they're working
on, show them, get them to at least a couple points of success.
I think with token maxing, obviously it's become a bit of a meme
now, as everybody saw the bills that sort of came due at the end of it.
Of course, I'm sure there was a way we could have gotten a lot
of these success stories without quite so many zeros on the end of the bill,
but there is a certain amount of you kind of have to just let it rip first,
find some things that work and get people excited and then reign it back in.
If you try to start from the beginning of being prudent,
you'll sort of undershoot the mark every time.
Yeah, let it rip.
And with that, maybe we should do questions.
Yeah, let's do some questions. Let him rip.
So we don't have microphones for folks.
So just shout them out.
Raise your hand. I'll call on you
and then I'll repeat the question for everybody we can go through.
So question for everybody.
What's our favorite recent factory technique or
something that you've tried that was really impactful or cool.
You want to take a first TV? You want me? Yes.
Fable lashing together a sled dog team of Opus.
Yeah, yeah.
It's going to be the new one, right?
I mean, I mean, for real, the technique
of getting smarter models to manage lower tier models,
that's going to be a game changer if you can dial that in.
Right. Because yeah. Yeah, yeah..
I think probably maybe a very specific one for me.
So I have developed a sort of recurring harness
that I'll for every new project that I work on, I'll put together
a big part of it.
A sweep, to use your parlance, is on test quality.
And I've added in mutation testing as a very particular.
So if folks aren't familiar, mutation testing is where you go in
and you permute the code in ways that should be breaking.
So you change boundary conditions on conditionals, or you will
change sort of magic numbers within the within the code.
And then you look to see if any of your tests.
We caught the what should have been a breaking change.
You can do this in two ways.
You can do it on a diff and it'll only make changes within the
effectively the PR you've put up.
Or you can do it across the whole code base.
And I swear by this now.
So I have it set up where every PR.
I so like it finds a bunch of stuff that coverage doesn't exactly.
Yeah. Yeah.
So the combination you'll set like a minimum bar on coverage.
Typically what I'll also do is set in PR like in CI, CD.
The PR that went up needs to have within the diff itself near 100% coverage.
So it's like you don't want to have a file that already has a lot of coverage.
A change within that sort of sneaks past.
But coverage can often be theater, so you want a way
to actually prove that the tests are catching real behavior.
So on every PR, I'll have mutation testing set up
where you don't want it to run directly because there can be false positives.
But I'll have an agent look at the results of a mutation testing report on the PR.
We'll leave comments for anything that wasn't caught, and it pretty much
always leads to an improvement in the test suite.
And then once a week, I'll do the same thing over the whole code base.
And that with that, I find my test suite is pretty reliable
and allows me to sort of get much closer to not reviewing the code.
What's like an example of coverage gap that have found where you're like, oh, I'm
very glad about that.
Probably the biggest one is in boundary conditions.
So there will be a lot of there is business logic
encoded in things like this list will never be empty.
And your test agents love to test things like once or twice.
So they'll do five and then 50 and they'll never check zero.
And so that's probably the biggest area I see it catching over and over again
is the little assumptions that you have baked
into your product that need to be represented in the code.
You want them to be in your test suite as well.
So the question was
how much of the factories that we build are deterministic versus
just relying on the model to do the right thing?
I call it the trust fall version of the of the factory.
Within Tessl.
We started very deterministic.
So we tried to have clear phases where the agent would build something.
And then we had our harness come in and create the PR and put it up.
We would
as comments were made, we would ferry them back down to the agent, at least for us.
I found we found pretty much you want to rip that out?
Like every piece of deterministic code you write that tries to orchestrate,
it becomes a source of brittleness in the factory.
And again, I'm saying this is from our perspective.
So what we found, it becomes brittle.
So it's pretty shocking the number of times
you think this is the truth for every single feature we build.
And then you realize,
oh, actually, like 15% of the features don't follow this pattern.
One simple one is like stacking PRS and you realize like,
oh crap, our orchestrator has made that physically impossible at this point.
So we've pulled back pretty aggressively to say,
you give the agent the GitHub CLI, you tell it what to do.
The main place we put deterministic checks are at the end.
So we have a bunch of hooks.
We have a bunch of like CI, CD like run the unit test suite, check to make sure
certain skills were loaded before you can stop things of that nature.
Yeah.
So the question was do we just operate with the hooks of the basic harness?
And I would say, yeah, like most of it is we will I'll use
as an example for myself, anytime the agent tries to do a tool call
to do a git push or a get commit,
run the unit tests and linter, and if they don't pass,
lock the tool, call and tell it.
You need to run these first and go fix them.
If it tries to stop session you check.
Is all your work committed?
Did you put up a PR?
If not, you can't stop. You need to go do that.
But otherwise my preference and Tessl were certainly a lot more.
Just lean on the agent.
I'm curious about you.
Oh excuse me, I think there's a lot of different ways you can kind of
like there's a couple of different ways you can like, think about determinism, but
one, one axis is, you know, open
claw versus gas town open claws.
Give the agents a goal and let them go swarm off and do it.
And Gas Town is break your work down into really small deterministic pieces
that they're going to execute in a specific order, right?
If the order matters.
Otherwise they can do it whatever order. Right.
But the idea is, is very different from open claw.
Right.
And so that's one way to look at it. Right.
Which is how much leeway do you give the agents versus
how much are you trying to like lay out what they're going to do.
Right.
There's another dimension to it, which is quality where you're trying to.
And it sounded to me like you were focusing on the quality dimension,
which is how do I make these things not make a mistake in one pass?
If you're talking about Lang chain, you're talking about
trying to keep things on the rails, trying to make them not skip one step.
And you're thinking about it fundamentally in terms of
how can I make it smarter in one pass?
And the answer is you wait for the next model drop.
I spent all of last year trying to code this.
I have a repo up on GitHub called Vibe Coder or maybe VC.
I have two of them where I tried
to solve this problem, and I realized that the answer?
You're just fighting the bitter lesson.
The answer is you do multiple passes and the answer is always swarming.
Swarm. Swarm. Swarm.
Adversarial.
Adversarial reviews consensus
like just like painting these walls here, don't think about
how can I build a machine that will paint the wall
perfectly on the first coat every time?
No multiple passes, multiple coats, right?
That's how that's how we code. So.
So factories have to be very stochastic and and quality becomes
a dial that you choose how many tokens you're going to spend on it.
Does that make sense?
Cool.
I think determinism of The Shape of Work is a good one too, though.
Like breaking things down into task trees.
I like that for SOC two compliance.
Yeah, exactly.
When we go here.
So the question was sort of philosophy to factory building.
Do you start from a top down and I will reinterpret a bit.
Tell me if I've gone too far off the rails, top down, sort of
start from a vision of how the system
should work from a central orchestrator that sort of builds outwards.
Or are you more bottoms up?
Like just start with a unit of work and then layer more on as you find what works.
Steve, what do you think?
Yeah.
So I mean, like I'm always reworking mine, right?
Like Gastown was like a perpetual rework until I got into a specific shape
that I particularly like, which is on the one side, I have a handful of agents
that I do deep design reviews with deep context.
It's like I call them a crew.
And on the other hand, there's the throwaway, ephemeral,
really well specified work that we're just going to throw agents at.
Right?
And that shape keeps recurring in my work because like, the throwaway
stuff is like, oh, I just have a big parallelizable thing.
I'm just going to split a fleet up, right?
So like, I keep making my way back to the Gastown shape.
But I started from first Principles again
recently, and I was building a software factory.
And it's interesting because you build it up by adding agents
and maybe letting them know about each other and you know,
they share work,
and it gets to a certain point and they're humming and you'll have like
12 agents run and you realize my factories the wrong shape.
I finally you know what I mean?
It's a stochastic process.
Also discovering what your factory looks like.
So you're like, God damn it,
I got to shut the whole thing down now and stop all the agents, let them drain.
Right, you know, and then, like, and then move all the directories around
and reshape the factory scripts and stuff.
So they all know where the new places are creating new clones or agents
that I need, and then boot the whole thing back up again and see how I like it.
Right.
And it takes it takes a few iterations, right?
And it seems I haven't figured out yet which parts are bespoke to the project
and which parts are generic that I'm going to bring along with me.
But boy, the faster
you can kind of set up and tear
down your factory, the better you're going to find your way to it.
Yeah.
Yeah, I think it's quite similar at Tessl.
And I'll do a light pitch here for the Tessl agent,
which tries to help you in building your software factory.
We take a very bottoms up iterative approach,
I think for two big reasons, or maybe three.
The first is everything is changing so fast, it's really hard
to just start from the top and get it all right as you go.
And it's much easier to say, here is a unit of work that I like.
Shape it around the work itself.
Like this is a task I know I do every week.
I just want to automate it.
And then you sort of layer on piece by piece.
You'll then have 4 or 5 automations that look kind of the same shape.
And so you'll build a thing that makes it easier to make that kind of automation.
And you sort of like a reverse jawbreaker, like you build up many layers
on top of it.
It's also the best way to actually get unstuck and start working.
I think anytime you try to ingest the entire software development lifecycle
in your head at once and say like, yes, I will design everything perfectly,
it's like a recipe
for spending two months figuring out something that won't even work at the end.
But again, if you just say, I do this every week,
what if I didn't have to do it? What if an agent did it?
What if agents bumped our versions every week?
Or what if agents ran mutation testing and then made our tests
a little bit better, or a little bit less flaky?
We found that that works a fair bit better.
And so that's the philosophy that our product takes
is just find one thing each week and make it a little bit better.
So the question was, how do you train people on
AI native development, but in a way that stays relevant,
doesn't grow out of date with the next model release or the next
new technique or new new tool.
I know you just had a post about this seat.
Maybe you want to. Take it.
I did, yeah.
Not to toot my own horn honk, but actually Netflix solved this problem for us.
Thank you Netflix. So I just posted about this.
It's called the Flat Curve Society.
It's a medium post I just did where I talk about a program
that Netflix presented that shows that there's an exact formula
for getting people over this hump, and it takes five hours,
but it has to be their manager and their work on working hours.
Blessed with a trainer, they were training our book as the curriculum.
Although you could train anything right?
They just have to be doing the real work and it's that immersion.
It's not really training, it's more like instructor led work, real work
and the whole the whole cohort.
If it's no more than ten people,
you can read all about it,
but basically they will all flip into the 4 million tokens a day category,
which is single agent synchronous throughout the work day.
And that is actually the moment where they have become
AI literate and they can start having real conversations with you.
Yeah, yeah.
I think probably the the most important thing is to get people
to some kind of an moment, because for a lot of folks,
it's not really that they need to be trained on AI.
They need to get excited enough that they go start training themselves on.
I like a lot of people are just afraid or they don't think it works,
or they're just put off by the hype of it all.
And so I think a lot of that Netflix training course is like, give people a day
blessed with their team, with their manager,
and just get them to a place where they are now excited to use agents.
And then a lot of stuff will come for free from that, right?
Like they'll just go do side projects, they'll try things.
They'll they'll test. Out they know how to.
They can now delete your database accidentally.
Exactly, exactly. That's what I thought.
Like I basically I feel like I do those trainings, I work at Google.
So you know, the culture and the streets.
I feel like I'm giving some people
a hammer and some people are using it in ways hammer shouldn't be used.
Well. Yeah, yeah, yeah.
I mean, so getting them to literacy and then multi-agent
literacy is like two steps of a ten step journey, right?
So the question was, any common components
that keep showing up, even if the factory itself is bespoke?
There's sort of like stock units that you use within it.
That's kind of your whole product, isn't it? Hopefully.
Yeah. Did you pay him?
Is that a show?
Yeah, yeah you can.
I'll pay PayPal you afterwards.
Know the certainly at Tessl we think that there are some
and we try to help with that.
So maybe I'll start with the ones that we've been building.
You want some way to connect your issue tracker to your source control.
So we have a Tessl app for linear and for GitHub.
Very basic.
All they do is you can delegate work to the linear app, and it will forward it
to the GitHub app so that you can kick off CI jobs
that run workflows you need that.
We didn't have that at first.
And we found and this is surprisingly common.
Maria shout out to Maria built our first orchestrator.
And so there was a period
where for like two weeks every PR and every comment was from Maria.
And there's just like identity issues there.
There's like nice UX pieces.
So how do you hook that up?
That's one thing that you're always going to want to build.
Another is some kind of a cloud environment for running agents.
So you can do it in GitHub actions.
It's not the cheapest if you run a lot of automations through GitHub actions,
and they're not the most suited for long running a genetic tasks.
So you have to like set up
sidecars, refresh your GitHub tokens, and it's not the best.
So it's just like a hosted service like that.
Somebody needs to build there.
There are I think some folks,
they tend to tie it to a broader like orchestration platform.
But there are tons.
There's factory, there's warp, there's Oz.
There's lots of folks who try to help here.
So there are ones you can pull off.
Tessl's one that's very simple.
It's just you use a skill to define a workflow,
and then we'll just run that in a cloud sandbox with access to GitHub.
And it can go as long as you want.
And then probably the biggest one outside of
those is a set of code review tools.
And so you want ways to do a genetic code review.
You want to know as I leave comments in addition to the agents comments,
are those getting
worked into the code review so that next time the agent will catch it,
you're going to want ways to do more specific checks.
So if Tessl, we have a thing called verifiers, which you can think of
as very, very focused linting rules that are powered by LNS.
So it allows you to do slightly more broad, vague things,
but still targeted to a specific file and a very focused check.
Like every JSX element must have Aria attributes on it,
and you can check those kind of things.
Follow up question was plumbing
between I'm guessing like workflow steps or things like that.
I would say for us, we found that those get in the way sooner than they like.
They outgrow their welcome very quickly.
And so we have moved to a world where most tasks are.
Just the single agent runs to completion,
and then you have a bunch of checks in CI that improve its quality.
And besides that, you're just running the GitHub CLI for it to interact.
Probably the main orchestration we run is in the task tracker itself.
So you'll create a parent task with things that are blocks and then blocks.
And that's like your that's effectively your Dag for execution.
But at this point we've built like six different orchestrators in Tessl.
And everyone starts with a lot of plumbing and ends with no plumbing,
because we always realized that it was more hassle than it was worth.
So the question was any unique challenges if you want to use local models
instead of the API frontier providers for building a software factory.
Steve, anything you want to jump with?
I think it's a huge market opportunity here for somebody to come along with like
hosted local models with a Claude Code
like hosted turnkey offering.
You know what I mean?
I mean just just a drop in replacement for Claude Code
that uses local models on on cheap inference, right?
Or even ideally finds a way to use whatever GPUs you have around.
Right?
I mean, I think like like people want off the Claude Code train
if they can find local models,
especially if we can fix that intelligence arbitrage problem.
Right.
Because then you get one Claude Max account to do all the planning
and you have the open source models do the implementation.
I think we're what, seven months away in December?
I think we should all have something there.
I can't imagine
we'll I'll still be paying anthropic for all of our tokens by next year.
Yeah.
Yeah, I think
probably the two big things I'd add to that for a while.
Folks have said like open source models haven't had their
like Sonnet 4.5 moment yet where it's like agents really got good.
I think some people think maybe GLM 5.2 might be
that problem is that's still going to have to be hosted, right?
Like GLM 5.2 is I think over a trillion parameters or something.
It's yeah I've seen the rig you need.
You need like. 20 or something.
Yeah. Yeah, exactly.
So probably the biggest thing you're going to face is just
for the foreseeable future, if you want truly local,
like I'm not renting anything, this is just sucking power from my outlet.
You're going to be limited to like, much smaller models.
And that's going to be tough as the distillation curve sort of brings
knowledge down.
But I think coming back to something you said, Steve,
you can just throw more tokens at it.
If anything, you can be even more gluttonous with tokens
because it's just power.
And so maybe connecting it back,
maybe you do need more orchestration than where you need to run a task through
like six, seven, eight review passes before you move on.
You can basically make up a lot of that intelligence,
so you might have more wiring than you have to do that.
This is this is why factories are so important.
It's because low tier models are always going to be important
because they're cheap and they can get stuff done, but
they need help being kept on the rails because they're low tier.
Right.
So the factories just they feel that space.
For me, I think it's the higher tier models come along.
You're going to use their
you're going to use them to just keep your factories on the rails.
But you're always going to use the lowest tier models you can.
Right. Yeah.
Yeah. The factory mindset I think
brings you into one of process optimization and monitoring.
Right.
Like you could use I don't know, I'm obviously going
to reveal a lack of physical knowledge about like real factories here.
But you could use the most titanium platinum coded screws
for every single thing and be like, okay, but I replace this piece of machinery
every two months, so why would I spend all the money on it?
I think one of the same thing with models, right, where maybe you use
Fable to plan, you use Opus to break down into milestones and then.
DeepSeek implements it. Yeah, exactly.
And I think getting good at that is going to become
a core competency of software engineering is you
look at not a given PR but a system that produces PRS.
How do I do that effectively.
So how often are we changing models versus using the same
maybe specifically for code review, but also just more generally.
I'm making a
push in that direction just because I don't really like
telling my wife I have five Claude Max accounts.
She's like, what is this?
So you know.
Yeah, right.
I think.
Because they're much better at reviewing than generating.
So you can generally go with like
a whole class lower and still get a pretty good review, right?
I. I think similar for me anytime.
And I think, Amy keep me honest in this as well.
I think if you get into the game of trying to pick a specific model
for your interactive
sessions, it's kind of a losing game because it's hard to anticipate
when a task is going to get complicated, when a mistake will be found.
And so I find most people who go that route,
they always end up doing the biggest, fastest model
or like best model they can afford all the time.
I think where it pans out a bit better is in the factory mindset.
If you can find a recurring task and sort of draw a box around it
and pull it out and say, here's a workflow that I do a lot, or here's a playbook
for adding a feature to the CLI, or shipping a front end change, etc.
once you have that now it's very fixed.
Like, you know, the task is going to go through how often it's going to fail.
That becomes a much better target for optimizing the right model.
And because it's something
you've put a box on, you're running all the time, it's worth it, right?
So code review is a great example there where code review is pretty stable right?
You can maybe have a few gates by complexity size of the diff.
And then it is actually consistent enough
that you can set a model for each type that you want to run.
Same with any automations that you create.
And so that, at least for me, is where I found more success.
And then Opus or Fable for any interactive session is like
it's my default at least.
All right.
Well thank you everybody. This is lovely.
Thanks. Cheers.
Oh, no. Oh!